Elizabeth Steel Genné Papers, 1952-2008
Sophia Smith Collection
Elizabeth Steel Genné papers
1952-2008
1957-1980
Genné, Elizabeth
MS 605
4 boxes (1.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA volunteer, Reproductive health advocate. The Elizabeth Steel Genné Papers are primarily related to her professional and public life. Types of materials include biographical materials, correspondence, minutes, reports, news clippings, notes, press releases, speeches, and memorabilia. The bulk of the papers date from 1957 to 1980 when Genné was a member of the National Board of the YWCA of the U.S.A., including a term as President, 1973-79. There are significant materials generated by Genné's committee work in the College and University Division of the YWCA in the 1950s and 60s. Genné served on the influential Committee to Study YMCA-YWCA Cooperative Experience (1959-60) which worked with Professor Dan Dodson to examine whether the YWCA should merge with the YMCA. There are also materials from the YWCA's Teen Sexuality Education Advisory Committee from the early 1980s.
Elizabeth Steel was born August 30, 1911 on a farm outside Albany, Oregon, to Charles and Winifred Steel. The family later moved to Portland, Oregon, where Elizabeth graduated from Washington High School. Steel's lifelong involvement in the YWCA began early at the Portland YWCA. In 1930 she attended the Christian Youth Conference of North America as President of the Portland YWCA Girl Reserve Club. There, she first met her future husband, William H. Genné.
Steel earned a B.Sc. from Oregon State College in 1935 and an M.A. from Teachers' College, Columbia University in 1936. She and William Genné were married in 1937. The couple had four children.
William Genné began a career as a college chaplain working at Michigan State University, Alfred University, and Pacific University over the next eighteen years. Meanwhile Elizabeth, who described herself as "primarily a homemaker and volunteer" worked in the Flint, Michigan, YWCA and as a teacher-counselor, teacher, staff in-service training lecturer, and Parent Education Consultant. During World War II she and her husband sponsored six interned Japanese-American students, making it possible for the students to complete college degrees.
Beginning in the 1950s the Gennés pioneered in the field of family life and sex education, working for the Clara Elizabeth Fund for Maternal Health in Flint, Michigan, and then the National Council of Churches from a home base in Montclair, New Jersey. They co-authored eight books and numerous articles and pamphletson family life, maternal health education, and sex education. The couple also gave joint presentations and organized workshops all over the U.S. and internationally.
In each of the cities where the Gennés lived, "Betty" was active in the local YWCA, usually serving on teen, college student, or young adult committees. Once the Gennés moved to New Jersey, she also began serving on national YWCA committees. Elected to the National Board in 1957, she continued as a member of that group until 1979, including a term as National President from 1973 to 1979. She is credited with helping the YWCA to make more effective use of its human and financial resources.
In addition to her volunteer activities for the YWCA, Betty Genné was active in the PTA, Montclair Civil Rights Commission, American Association of University Women, League of Women Voters, United Council of Church Women, and UNICEF.
The Gennés retired to Claremont, California in 1984. William Genné died in 1997. Three years later Betty married Stanley Conover, who died in 2006.
Elizabeth Steel Genné died on February 29, 2008 in Claremont, California.
The Elizabeth Steel Genné Papers consist of 1.75 linear ft. and are primarily related to her professional and public life, dating from 1952 to 1984. Types of materials include biographical materials, correspondence, minutes, reports, news clippings, notes, press releases, speeches, and memorabilia.
The bulk of the papers date from 1957 to 1980 when Genné was a member of the National Board of the YWCA of the U.S.A., including a term as President, 1973-79. Genné served on a number of committees examining particularly difficult issues during turbulent times for the Association from the 1960s to the early 1980s. There are significant materials generated by Genné's committee work in the College and University Division of the YWCA in the 1950s and 60s. Genné served on the influential Committee to Study YMCA-YWCA Cooperative Experience (1959-60) which worked with Professor Dan Dodson to examine whether the YWCA should merge with the YMCA. The Committee's final report, known internally as the "Dodson Report," urged the YWCA to reaffirm its role as an autonomous women's organization. There are also materials from the YWCA's Teen Sexuality Education Advisory Committee from the early 1980s.
A small amount of material from Genné's work for the YWCA on the local and state level in New Jersey is also included.
The Speeches files include texts, programs, clippings, and correspondence about local arrangements, primarily from Genné's term as President of the National YWCA. They are filed chronologically.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
The Elizabeth Steel Genné Papers came to the Sophia Smith Collection with the Records of the YWCA of the U.S.A. in 2002. Elizabeth Genné donated them to the YWCA in 1984.
Genné, Elizabeth; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. -- History -- Sources
Associated material located in the YWCA USA Records, Sophia Smith Collection
- Biographical materials and miscellaneous 1952-2008, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Montclair (New Jersey) YWCA
  - Board of Directors 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Right to Live Conference, Nov 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- New Jersey State Council of YWCAs 1974-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- YWCA of the U.S.A.
  - General 1957-83, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Committees
    - Fleischmann Project (Leadership Development Center) 1979-83, undated (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Leadership Development Goal Group 1980-82 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Program and Budget Apportionment Committee 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Teen Sexuality Education Advisory Committee
      - General 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Site reports 1981-82 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Utilization of National Volunteers Subcommittee
      - 1978-79 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1980-82, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Convention
    - 1961-81, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Learning Center X, Presidential Leadership and Association Committee Chairpersons' Workshop (faculty) 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Public Affairs
    - General 1973-81 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Abortion 1973-80, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Gun control 1973, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Student/College and University Division
    - Anniversary (110th) Tea, Apr 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Consultation on Future Relationships of YWCA to New York State Student Christian Movement 1958-59 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - National Student YWCA Administrative Committee
      - 1957-59 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
      - 1960-64 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Proposal to Ford Foundation for Training Program for a Leadership Cadre on Urban Affairs Related to a National Student Assembly (NSAY) Dec 1966-Jan 1967 1965-66 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Regional Advisory Committee 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - World YWCA Pre-Council Consultation on Work with Students 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - YMCA
    - Committee to Study YMCA-YWCA Cooperative Experience ("Dodson Study") 1959-60 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Consultation on YM-YW Relationsips 1971 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "YWCA Looks to the Future" Year One meetings (convenor) 1979-82 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Speeches
  - Miscellaneous 1968-80, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Burlington County (NJ) YWCA 50th Anniversary Apr 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New Castle County (DE) YWCA Annual Meeting Apr 1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Philadelphia (PA) YWCA Friendship Fete Luncheon Apr 1975 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Nashville (TN) YWCA 75th Anniversary Apr 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Knoxville (TN) YWCA and Travelers Aid Annual Meeting May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Memphis (TN) YWCA Annual Meeting May 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Savannah (GA) YWCA Annual Meeting Jan 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Detroit (MI) YWCA Annual Meeting Feb 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Charlotte (NC) YWCA Annual Meeting Feb 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Buffalo and Erie County (NY) YWCA Annual Meeting Feb 1976 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Roanoke Valley (VA) YWCA Annual Meeting Mar 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Sioux Falls (SD) YWCA Leader Luncheon III May 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - High Point (NC) YWCA Annual Meeting Jan 1977 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Southern Methodist University Symposium '77 Feb 1977 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - San Antonio (TX) YWCA Dedication of Recreation Center Feb 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Canton (OH) YWCA Annual Meeting Mar 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American Association of University Women, Indiana State Division Convention Apr 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Fort Wayne (IN) YWCA Annual Meeting Apr 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - St. Louis (MO) YWCA Biennial Dinner Jan 1978 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Columbia (SC) YWCA Annual Meeting Jan 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Mountain Lakes Women Jan 1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Danville (VA) YWCA Annual Meeting Feb 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - York (PA) YWCA Annual Meeting Feb 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Bethlehem (PA) YWCA 50th Anniversary Apr 1978 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - San Francisco (CA) YWCA Centennial Jun 1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - High Point (NC) YWCA Women in Society lecture series Nov 1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Dallas (TX) YWCA Sustaining Membership Campaign Kickoff Feb 1979 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Salt Lake City (UT) YWCA Annual Meeting Apr 1979 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Summit (NJ) YWCA Annual Meeting Feb 1980 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Durham (NC) YWCA Annual Meeting Apr 1980 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Plainfield and Westfield (NJ) TWIN Dinner Jun 1980 (Box 4, Folder 21)